Today, let's take a look at why, as an AI product manager
Why is it necessary to master data capabilities
Let's take a look at these three aspects
The first is from the algorithmic perspective,
Second, we look at it from the perspective of data-driven
from the perspective of model iteration
Third, from the perspective of utilizing data
Let's take a look at the first one
From the perspective of algorithms
As we know, the model is trained from data combined with algorithms
support our business scenarios
This is called AI, and if there is no data
we cannot train this model
Therefore, you can't make bricks without straw.
Data is very important
For example, if we want to develop an intent recognition model
So when we train this model,
we need data
Then we may need to annotate this data
labeled as positive
negative or neutral
For example, we have labeled 1,000 pieces
Then use these 1,000 pieces to train such a model.
The labeling for this scenario is relatively simple
we may not need documentation
However, within enterprises
There are many complex annotation scenarios
For these complex annotation scenarios
As an AI product manager
You need to output the corresponding annotation documentation.
This annotation document may specify
What are the specific labeling standards you have?
What is the data review process after your labeling?
Let's look at another example
Our large model requires fine-tuning.
For fine-tuning
As a product manager
We need to promote the implementation of the corresponding fine-tuning data.
Then we need to check what issues exist with this data
First of all, you need to understand SQL
Now, if you don't know SQL
then give you a piece of data
you wouldn't know how to look at it
For example, in this dataset
As you can see, there's a field here called label
This is the labeling for each piece of data.
labeled user intent
So do you need to write SQL
check the user intent in this, and there is a long
there is another table
Is it consistent with the user intent system
If they are inconsistent
then this data may be problematic
Additionally, you need to understand
how to evaluate the quality of this data
If you are given a set of data
You don't know whether this data has anomalies
has missing data, you are also unaware
you don't know if it's duplicated
If the data quality cannot be guaranteed
At that point, the algorithm engineers receive this set of data
the performance of the trained model will be very poor
Let's look at the second aspect
from the perspective of data-driven product iteration
After we launch this model
We need to assess how well this model performs
We need to break down the metrics
For example, still in the context of smart customer service
What is the accuracy of user intent recognition?
Has the manual transfer rate decreased?
what is the proportion of incorrect intents
Then we need to use this data
can identify what problems still exist in the model
so as to guide
the direction for our next iteration of the model
Another important role is that for R&D
for products, for operations
have their own Follow metrics
these metrics
we build a dashboard
facilitating all parties to align with this objective
Thirdly, from the perspective of utilizing data
We need to consider two issues
why many companies fail to implement AI
Why do some companies achieve poor implementation results
Let's take a look at this scenario
have the large model analyze
improvement measures for a certain production workshop
Now if you let the large model analyze
You need to provide it with granular data.
If you don't have data
It cannot find any reason
It can only tell you to replace the factory manager
So you need to provide it with data, what kind of data?
such as what materials
what process
factors of a certain step, etc.
The finer the granularity of the data, the better
it can then analyze
which part has room for improvement
Therefore, if we want to make good use of AI
the data foundation of the enterprise is crucial
Finally, let's summarize
As an AI product manager
We need to understand data
because this capability is truly crucial